Um, let's get started. This is uh 1401
uh microeconomics. Uh the uh
and um I'm Professor John Gruber.
Now, couple notes about the course. Uh
there's a distinct policy angle to this
course. Um I think personally what makes
economics most exciting is it can you
you can use it to think intelligently
about the problems that policy makers
face every day as they try to decide how
to make the economy work the best for
its citizens. Um in fact, I teach a
whole course about this called 1441. Uh
but I'm going to bring some of those
insights into this class and use
policy-based examples and things like
that to try to motivate uh and organize
our thinking about economics.
Um lastly, uh three points about my
teaching style.
First of all, I don't write everything
on the board. Uh for the freshmen here,
we're not in high school anymore. You
need to pay attention and listen to what
I say, not just what I write. Um so it's
important to remember that. Um uh
I uh the second point is as you can
tell, I talk really fast and my
handwriting is really bad.
Okay? So please please don't be afraid
to ask what the hell I just said or
wrote. Okay? There is if you don't know,
chances are at least 40% of the class
doesn't know either.
We'll learn later semester about the
concept of a public good. A public good
is something you do which has a personal
cost and a social benefit. I understand
raising your raising your hand in a
class as large as this can be
intimidating, but remember in doing so,
you're not just helping yourself, you're
helping your fellow classmates. So
please don't lean and whisper loudly,
"What the hell did he just say?" to the
person next to you. Raise your hand and
ask me because if you didn't understand,
many other people didn't as well.
More generally, it's hard to get class
participation in a class this large, but
I really encourage people to participate
as much as possible.
I've never had a year in this class
where there's been too much
participation. I've had every single
year too little participation. So,
please follow up with questions, uh
things like that.
And then finally, the third point about
my teaching style is I have a bad
tendency to use the term guys in a
gender neutral sense.
So, when I say guys, I don't mean men. I
mean economic agents, people,
everyone. And I'm sorry guys is a
gendered word. Often I don't mean it
that way. It's just kind of uh economist
talk for for economic agents. We call
them guys.
What we're going to do today is talk
about what is microeconomics. What are
you going to learn in this course? What
is the basic field about?
And then we'll dive in next time into
actually starting to learn about the
models that make up basic
microeconomics.
Um
microeconomics
is fundamentally in a sentence
the study of how individuals and firms
make themselves as well off as possible
in a world of scarcity.
It's how individuals and firms make
themselves as well off as possible in a
world of scarcity.
Scarcity is key.
The core of microeconomics
is constrained optimization.
Basically, individuals or firms
assessing the tradeoffs
they face every day
in the decisions they make, and then
trying to decide the best decision given
those tradeoffs.
So, that is microeconomics is really
about tradeoffs. Microeconomics is
really about you can't have it all.
So, what are you going to do with what
you can have? How are you best going to
use your limited resources?
And the key concept behind all this, the
sort of probably the
I'm going to say about a hundred times,
this is one of the most important
concepts in economics. I'm sorry about
that, but this is really one of the most
important concepts in economics, is the
concept of opportunity cost.
Opportunity cost.
Okay? An opportunity cost is the notion
that every action
or inaction
has cost in terms of what you could have
done instead, in terms of the next best
opportunity.
If you buy a shirt,
you are foregoing spending that money on
buying something else. So, if you decide
between shirts and pants, you buy the
shirt, you're foregoing buying the pair
of pants.
If you study,
if you spend all night studying, you're
foregoing the opportunity to go see a
band you like in concert. And vice
versa.
Every action you take
is a trade-off. Every decision you make
involves a trade-off cuz there's always
an opportunity cost. There's always
something you could have done instead.
Yeah.
Uh great question.
Um actually, let me come back to that in
1 minute. I'm going to come back to
that.
Or 5 minutes.
Um Okay. So, this is why
economics is called the dismal science.
We're called the dismal science because
the role of the economist is to
basically say, "Well, you think that's
free, but it's not.
You think you can just relax and watch
TV, but you know that by watching TV
you're giving up the opportunity to
study, the opportunity to go out and see
a concert, or the opportunity to
something else."
Okay? So, that's why it's called the
dismal science. Now, some people may
call it dismal, I call it fun, and maybe
that's cuz I was an MIT undergraduate.
And what is an engineering school but
the land of constrained optimization?
That's what engineering and science is.
It's all about what engineering is. It's
constrained optimization. What better
example could there be than the 2.007
contest where you're given a set of
materials and asked to build something?
That's a constrained optimization
exercise. Indeed, economics was invented
modern economics invented at MIT by the
economist Paul Samuelson, who
essentially said the mathematics that
sciences and engineers engineers use can
be applied to analyze really the sort of
essay-like approach that people had
taken in economics before him.
So, he basically brought the tools of
science to economics and basically
developed the course I'll teach today
and the course that's taught all over
the world was developed right here at
MIT. Modern economics is born here
because we introduce the tools of
constrained optimization.
Now,
oh, over here I'm usually going to try
to do like an outline of what we're
covering. So, we talked about course
details, what is micro? I just did that.
talk about how we do that. What
economics does, which is we use models
and I'm talking about a model of supply
and demand.
How do we actually teach you all about
these tradeoffs?
Okay?
The way we do it is by building
simplified models. Okay, what is a
model? A model is technically the
description of any relationship between
two or more variables
is a model.
Um,
now, but unlike explain the relationship
between energy and mass, we do not have
scientific laws and constants in our
universe. Okay? Economics is, as much as
we hate to say it, not a real science.
It is a social science.
Which means that basically we don't have
rigid laws that we can write down and
say they're all they're everywhere
applicable.
Okay? We we have to use models to
basically try to explain the world as
much as we can. And so, in doing so, we
have to make a set of simplifying
assumptions.
A set of simplifying assumptions to try
to essentially trade off two goals.
One goal is to explain as much as we
can.
The other goal is to have parsimonious
models that I can teach you.
Okay? The more complicated the model
gets, the harder it is to teach, the
harder it is to solve. This comes to the
earlier question about are you really
just trading off two goods? Well, of
course you're never just trading off two
goods.
But, we're going to write our models
like you are.
And it's going to turn out that gives
you all the intuition you need for a
model with just three or four goods.
It's just a lot easier math.
So, it turns out everything you learn in
a model with two goods tells you
everything you need to know for a model
with n goods.
Just with easier math. So, that's the
kind of simplifying assumption. That's a
fairly
um uh that's a fairly uh non-offensive
simplifying assumption because it
doesn't really change anything. We'll
make other simplifying assumptions which
are noxious and offensive.
And we'll talk about those. And if you
are offended by them and bothered and
want to see what happens without those
assumptions, then that's exactly why you
should be economics major.
Because that's really what we go on and
do in the rest of the classes. Say,
"Okay, now let's move on from these
simplified models, add some richness,
and see what it does to the world."
Okay?
Uh the statistician George Box uh once
wrote that all models are wrong, but
some are useful.
Okay? And that's exactly what we're
going to try to work with today.
Okay? When I teach you economics, I'm
going to try to teach it to you on three
levels.
Okay, the first one for MIT is
mathematical.
The second is graphical, and the third
is intuitive.
Really, if you want to succeed in this
class, you need to understand all three.
Now, not every model will I use all
three.
But, you want to understand all three of
those concepts to really understand the
material we're learning here.
And we'll start with the model of supply
and demand. The very first economic
model developed by Adam Smith in 1776 in
the book that was sort of the founding
of economics, The Wealth of Nations.
Adam Smith asked the question, um
think about two goods. Think about water
or think about diamonds.
Okay?
Nothing is more essential for life than
water. We cannot function without it.
Nothing is probably less essential for
life than diamonds, especially back then
when diamonds didn't have industrial
uses. They were just baubles.
Okay? Water is clearly just essential.
Diamonds aren't. Yet, the price of
diamonds is very high and water's
essentially free.
He asked, "How could this be?"
And the answer is because what I've just
described is only one half of the model
of where we get the price of water or
diamonds.
I've described the demand.
I've described the demand
for water and diamonds. I've said the
demand for water is much, much larger
than the demand for diamonds.
What I haven't talked about is the
supply.
Which is that the supply of water is
even more
relative to supply of diamonds. Water's
everywhere, diamonds are rare to find.
And what Adam Smith said is that while
the demand for diamonds may not be as
high as the demand for water, the supply
of diamonds is much, much smaller than
the supply of water.
And that is why you can end up with a
good that's inherently less valuable to
life
having a higher price.
Okay? And Smith's point is you can't
just think of supply and demand in
isolation.
You need to think of them
uh together. Um is uh Oh, Pedro, could
you grab me a copy of the handout?
Thanks.
Um
Okay. So, that's sort of the intuition.
That's the intuition supply and demand
model. Now, let's talk about the
graphics and the math.
Okay? So, now let's talk about an
example of a supply and demand model.
And let's focus on the market for roses.
What is a market? A market's what it
sounds like. It's buyers and sellers
coming together.
Are there any more any extra handouts
around?
Does everyone have one?
Does everyone have a handout?
Okay, good. That's fine then. Okay,
let's talk about the the markets for di-
Let let's talk about the market for
roses.
Okay? First of all, what is a market?
A market is Think of a market to start.
Yeah.
Like another page, right?
The handout has graphs on it.
Does anyone have the handout?
Did you tell me to print?
What's that? Is there any Is there an
extra pile sitting around there of
handouts?
We've got some extras there. Okay, pass
those around. Make sure
you know, pass those around and uh
Yeah, next time I said the the they'll
be in the back. So, please, you know,
raise your hand if you don't have a
handout and let's try to pass those
around.
Okay? Hey, dude, can you grab one for
me?
Um okay. So, basically, let's think
about the market for roses. What is a
market?
A market is a place where buyers and
sellers come together to make
transactions. Okay?
Think of it like the old-timey markets
of ancient England, where literally the
only way to transact was physically
being in the same place,
where the buyers and sellers would come
to market once a week and the people
would bring their cows and people who
wanted milk would come in or meat would
come in and they would transact. Think
of the market that way. Now, of course,
that's not how the modern market works,
but that's the way we want you to
intuitively think of a market. It's
literally a place where buyers and
sellers are interacting.
And it turns out that intuition will
work even even given the modern economy.
Okay?
So, now, who else doesn't have handouts?
Everyone got the graphs?
Okay. All right. So, um now, let's talk
about the market for roses.
In figure 1.1,
we have the market for roses.
Okay? On the x-axis, the horizontal
axis, we have the quantity of roses. I'm
going to, by the way, try to have
handouts for all the graphs cuz my
handwriting's so brutal. So, uh
uh you shouldn't have to see Hopefully,
if all goes well this semester, you
should never see me draw a graph on the
board.
Um so, uh
on the x-axis, we have the quantity of
roses. On the y-axis, we have the price
of roses.
Okay? Um the demand curve represents the
relationship between price and quantity
from the consumer's perspective.
So, the demand curve in this case is
represented by the equation
Q =
1,800
- 400 P.
Okay, now you immediately say, "Well,
what's Where's 1,800 400 come from?" It
doesn't matter right now.
That's what we're going to teach you in
the next few lectures. Right now, that's
just That's an equation that represents
a line.
And it's The critical aspect of that
equation is that there's a negative
relationship
between
price and quantity.
As price goes up, consumers want fewer
roses.
Why is that? Well, it's just because of
opportunity cost.
The more expensive is a rose, the more
you have to give up to buy it.
So, its opportunity cost is higher, so
you want it less.
Okay? So, the higher is the price, the
fewer roses you want. So, we get a
downward-sloping
demand curve.
The The blue line.
Now, the supply curve represents the
same relation between price and
quantity, but from the suppliers'
perspective.
A supply curve in this case that we've
drawn here has the equation Q
= 200 P.
200 P.
You'll see here there is a positive
relationship
between price and quantity.
That is, the supply curve is
upward-sloping.
As price goes up, firms will Firms will
produce more roses. Why? Once again,
opportunity cost.
With a low price, producing a rose means
you can't use that farm to produce
something else.
If the price of roses is low, you're
going to use the farm for something
else. If the price of roses is high,
you will then use that farm to produce
roses, cuz that is a better choice than
the next best alternative.
So, once again, this concept of
opportunity cost has already helped
explain the basic model of economics.
The single most important model of
economics is represented in this graph.
And you can understand it just by the
concept of opportunity cost.
That is why we are such a powerful
social science. That's why all the other
social sciences are jealous of
us.
Okay? Because we can use simple tools to
explain much to explain much of the
world. And here's a perfect example.
Okay? Now, we call the point
where those two curves meet the
equilibrium.
The point where supply and demand
are in agreement is the equilibrium.
That is the point at which suppliers are
willing to sell roses
at the same price consumers are willing
to pay for them.
So, with 600 roses, 600 box of roses, or
whatever it is,
the the equilibrium price
is $3. Well, it's a rose, so it with 600
roses, equilibrium price is $3. That is
both parties are happy in equilibrium.
The key point about equilibrium,
as the name implies,
as the term equilibrium implies, it's
the point where
the system has come to rest.
Where both parties are happy with the
outcome. Both parties are happy because
it's on the demand and supply curve.
Since it's on the demand curve,
consumers are willing to pay
$3 for 600 roses.
They wouldn't pay $4 for 600 roses,
but they'd pay three.
Since it's on the supply curve,
suppliers are willing to accept $3 for
600 roses. They wouldn't accept $2 for
600 roses, but they'll accept $3 cuz
it's on the curve.
So, basically, it's just two equations
and two unknowns.
You set these two things equal to each
other, and you solve, and you get Q star
equals uh Q star equals 600,
and P star
equals three. Just by two equations and
two unknowns. Once again, why we only
have two goods? I could have done this
in three dimensions. The graph would
have been uglier, but the math would
have been harder, but nothing would have
changed. Yeah.
Oh, that's a great question. Basically,
they are
It's a good question. We write down the
functions are basically invertible and
we use them both ways is the bottom
line. It doesn't We're really writing
down equilibrium in Q and P. It doesn't
really matter what X and Y is. We're
really just writing down an equilibrium
relationship. It's just the convention
is to put Q on the X axis, even though
the
even though the convention will
sometimes write demand curves with P on
the left-hand side. The graphic
eventually will never change, but how I
write the curves might change. How I
write the equations might change. Yeah.
Great question. Okay, let's go through
it. That's exactly the kind of question
I want to hear this semester. The reason
demand is a Why don't you take a crack
at it?
Anyone Anyone want to explain? Yeah.
And speak up.
If the price is higher to in order to
get that rose, you had to give up more
because the price represents sort of
like your opportunity
Right. Price The opportunity cost of any
good in the free market is its price.
So, as the as the price goes up, the
opportunity cost goes up. Why? Because
there's more other stuff you could have
bought.
So, if it's three bucks a rose, you
could have bought, you know, a slice of
pizza and a coke. But it's four buck If
it's If it's four bucks a rose, you
four bucks a rose, you don't have enough
money left to buy both the coke and the
and the slice of pizza. So, and but
that's a great question cuz that's
exactly where we're going to go next. Is
the next three lectures are going to
tell you where this equation comes from.
We're going to start with the basic
principles of people's preferences.
Really almost philosophical. And we're
going to derive this curve.
Then after that, the next five lectures
will be deriving this curve.
We'll start with the basic principles of
how firms make decisions.
And we'll derive the supply curve. Yeah.
Um so, when you say $3, is that per rose
or is that for a certain quantity of
roses or for one rose?
Well, it depends on on what I've written
on the axis. You're right. This is this
is confusing. Page, you should make a
note. We should probably make this
clearer next time. We should have called
this number of roses or shouldn't have
been called quantity of roses. That's a
great point. We should call this number
of roses or boxes of roses. But it's per
a quantity that's specified in the
model.
Okay.
Great question.
Think of MIT. You cannot get away with
with sloppiness here. I love it.
Harvard, what the hell? You write
whatever you want. Yeah.
Um are the supply and demand curves
usually linear or are they often
non-linear?
Great question. Indeed, uh this is
another cheat we'll do, which we'll
often write down non-linear
representations but draw them linearly.
Um this is a linear representation, but
sometimes we'll have non-linear curves
and draw them linearly. But when we do,
think of it as a local approximation.
Think of the linear piece as a local
approximation to the larger function.
Okay, great questions. I love it. Okay.
Now,
this raises this model raises a very
important distinction
that we're going to focus on this
semester and it's going to trip you up,
I guarantee you a number of times. So, I
want you to be very careful thinking
about this,
which is the distinction between
positive
economics
and normative economics.
Positive economics
is the study of the way things are,
while normative economics
is the study of the way things should
be.
Okay, positive economics study the way
things are.
Normative economics is the study of the
way things should be.
Okay?
Now, to consider to understand this,
let's consider a great example of
economics at work,
which is eBay.
Okay?
When eBay came along,
okay, I know it is older than all of
you, but it's younger than me. When eBay
came along, economists were very excited
because economists love auctions.
Auctions are, if you will, the standard
market that used to exist in, you know,
15th century England. Okay? It's
literally people bidding against each
other
in a way that reveals who wants the good
the most.
And what's wonderful about that, and
we'll come back to this throughout the
semester, is it has two great features.
One is it makes sure the right amount
gets produced, and two is it makes sure
the people who want it the most get it.
One beautiful feature of free markets
is that they don't just get you to the
right aggregate quantity, they also get
the get the goods in the hands of people
who are willing to pay the most for
them.
And that's what what eBay did.
Now, one auction eBay got a lot of
example got a lot of attention, I'm
sorry. Got a lot of attention.
Which is that somebody put their kidney
for auction on eBay.
They auctioned their kidney. And they
said, "I'll give you my kidney for Let
the bidding start at $25,000."
The bidding got up to $5 million before
eBay shut it down and said, "No
auctioning human body parts on eBay."
Okay?
Now, I don't know why they stopped at $5
million utterly, but whatever. Okay. So,
we can with this example, we can ask
both a positive and a normative
question.
The positive question is, "Why did the
price get so high?"
And here, we only need appeal to supply
and demand model.
The demand for a kidney is going to be
pretty high. If you need a kidney to
live, you're going to pay approximately
everything you have to get it.
The supply of kidneys on the free market
is pretty low. Like, that was the only
one I know of.
Okay? So, it's a classic case of a very
high demand and a very low supply,
you're going to get a very high price.
And so, it's not surprising the price
went up and probably would have gone up
further if eBay hadn't shut it down.
But, now we come to the normative
question, which is more interesting and
harder.
Which is um should we be allowed to sell
our bodily organs on eBay?
Okay? You might think that this is a
question you're in philosophy class, but
fundamentally this is an economics
question.
Okay? Many folks die in America because
the because we do not have enough organs
to help those with organ failure. We we
have a limited supply of organs. I hope
you all are organ donors on your
driver's licenses. Doesn't cost you
anything, you're gone anyway, and it can
save a life.
Um but um many people don't do that and
uh even if they did, we're just we have
a higher demand for organs than we can
fit. Now, if someone
who wants an organ
is wealthy
and willing to pay a lot of money for
it.
And there's someone else
who says, "Look, I got two kidneys. You
can function just fine with one.
The odds of kidney failure is really
low."
Someone says, "Look, I am in desperate
straits.
I can't feed my family. I can't how
house my family.
I can sell one kidney, still function
fine, and change my life forever.
Educate my children, build a house, do
things I need to do.
Why shouldn't we let that happen?
So, standard economics
would say
great, let them auction their body
parts.
But in fact
there's reasons why
we don't think
men there's many reasons why that may
not be a good outcome.
What are those? What are reasons we
might not want to just say, "Sure, let
her rip."?
What are some reasons?
Yeah.
Go ahead, do you share?
Yeah. So, there's fundamentally two
kinds of reasons.
The first kind is what we'll call market
failures.
Market failures are something we're not
going to cover for about the first
11 lectures. For the first 11 lectures,
the free market is going to be king.
Let me be very clear with you. Economics
is fundamentally a right-wing science.
Okay, as will come clear through the
semester, I'm kind of a left-wing guy,
but economics is pretty much a
right-wing science. And a basic
economics says the market knows best.
And the And there's only two reasons why
you should ever interfere with the
market.
And the first is cuz for some reason the
market's not working properly. This is
an example.
We It would be fine if I would
knowledgeably went into this
transaction.
But what if this turns out this can
cause people to like
force force their children to give up
their kidney
or do things against their will
or other criminal activities.
Um what if people don't really
understand
how dangerous it is to give your kidney?
There's 50,000 Americans every year
There's now currently about 100,000
Americans living with hepatitis C, which
causes kidney failure.
Hepatitis C can live dormant for years
before you know you have it.
What if you give up your kidney and find
out you have hepatitis C? Then you're
dead.
So, there's lots of reasons why I think,
well, maybe this market doesn't work
quite as well as economists say it does.
People might be misinformed. People
might be
people might be forced
to do it.
What's interesting is the black market
is not necessarily one of those reasons.
And here's why.
Because the black market economists just
say is a market.
Let's say eBay doesn't allow you to sell
your kidneys, so you have to go sell it
on the black market.
Well, if there's no other market
failures, that's okay. For the same
reason economists think it'd be okay to
sell your body parts, there's no reason
why you sell your body parts on a formal
market and informal market. The only
reason why it would be bad would be if
that informal market comes with other
unsavory features, like forcing people
to sell their body parts or not being
informed. That's when it'd be bad.
Okay? What other reasons might might
care? Might we worried about people
selling the kidneys.
Yeah, white t-shirt in the back.
It would mean that only like really rich
people would be able to get them.
Great Great answers, guys. The second
reason we care is what we call equity
or fairness,
which is we might not think it's fair
that rich people get to live and poor
get to live longer and buy their organs
if poor people don't.
Okay, we might think this is that that
this is an unfair outcome.
Now, this is what's fascinating about
America,
which is even though we pride ourselves
on being the land of the market economy,
we also care a lot about fairness
as a nation.
And this is viewed by many as being
blatantly unfair, that the richer you
are, the more you can just buy part body
parts off poor people.
Now, here's what's a little bit sad
about this class and the sad about the
limitation of only having, you know, the
number of weeks we have, which is I'm
not going to talk nearly as much about
equity as I'd like to.
90% of this course is going to be about
efficiency.
It's going to be about does the market
work? Does the market deliver the right
quantity of goods?
It's not about equity, which is well,
does that right quantity end up going
end up causing huge inequality in
society?
So, that is kind of another reason why
we might care. Okay, and we will discuss
equity later in the semester, but
unfortunately not till much later.
All right? Other questions or thoughts
about that?
Okay.
Let me finally talk about one last
thing,
which sort of seems like you got to talk
about in the first lecture of any of any
economics class, which is what about the
underlying structure of the economy? How
do we think about different models of
how economies function? And the
fundamental conflict is between a
capitalist model
and a command model.
The capitalist model in its purest form,
what's called the laissez-faire or let
it be
uh model, is one where individuals
decide what to produce and consume
with no interference.
It's a purely free market.
Okay? It's a market that sort of existed
500 years ago.
Before we had sort of They The The truth
is it never existed. There's no such
thing. We will do a lot of teaching by
extremes in this course. We'll talk
about extremes. It's a great learning
device, but there's not never been such
a thing as a purely capitalist economy.
Most economies, like the US,
are market-driven, but government and
socially constrained. What does that
mean? That means, yes, we let GM decide
how many cars to produce, but we have
standards on what emissions those cars
can have and how safe they have to be.
In a purely capitalist economy, GM could
produce the most dangerous cars they
wanted.
No one would care, and they could be
smog-laden and no one would care.
Obviously, we don't have that in
America.
We have regulations. We have taxes on
gas. We have rules on what you can learn
and where you can learn it, etc. So, we
have what we call a sort of constrained
capitalist economy, where fundamentally
the decisions on what to produce and
what to consume are made by individuals
within a set of rules set up by the
government and some also set up by
social norms.
Okay?
Now, the opposite
extreme is what we call a command
economy, and we actually had almost the
closest model that could exist to this,
which was the Soviet Union of my youth.
The Soviet Union of my youth, it's
typically associated with communism,
although it doesn't have to be. Command
economies don't have to be associated
with communism. Germany in World War II
was a command economy in the service of
fascism.
It's typically associated with communism
is what we call a command economy. In In
that extreme, the government makes all
production allocation decisions.
People won't decide what they get. The
government decides what they get.
So, it's the other extreme. There's no
free transactions.
It's the government making all the
rules, not just about
how much to be produced, but who gets
what's produced.
Okay, so in the free market, the market
subjects that of government sort of you
guys are bold, there's like the bumpers
you come up when you're a little kid and
you bowl and they keep the ball on that
bowling lane.
So, think of the government, you know,
in a capitalist economy is those sort of
those those those um guides on the side
that help keep the ball in the lane.
But but you get to throw the ball and
decide where you're going to which pin
you're going to go for. In a command
economy, they literally they tell you go
to the end of the lane and knock down
pin seven.
Okay?
Uh it's a very it's a very different
model.
Now,
in theory,
the argument for the command model
is that it can ensure
that the right goods get produced and
distributed as fairly as possible.
The idea this the theory is quite
simple. It goes back to Karl Marx. The
theory makes a lot of sense.
Which is look, the government's job is
to make sure society is well off as
possible.
It does that by making sure the right
things get produced
and get to the right people.
And we can't trust the market to do
that, only the government could do that.
Okay? This is a great argument in
theory, in practice it doesn't work.
And it doesn't work for two reasons.
It First of all, it's just too damn hard
to make all those decisions.
Any government, no matter how large and
how benevolent, cannot make the enormous
massive quantity of billions and
billions of decisions that need to be
made. Think about every good we consume
in America. A government deciding how
much of it to make and literally who
gets it.
Okay? It's overwhelming. Governments
can't do it. That led to things like in
East Germany. I was in East Germany a
year ago and I went to the went to the
museum of East Germany and uh they talk
about how in and back in communist days
in East Germany, uh no one had cars, but
they had so much bread they would feed
bread to their pigs for food.
Okay? Because the government sort of
screwed up and decided make, you know,
commanded too many too much bread and
too few cars.
Okay? That's natural. It's going to
happen. It's just too hard.
Okay? The second problem is that human
nature being what it is, a command
economy inevitably leads to massive
corruption.
Because when a handful of people are in
charge of deciding everything, of course
they're going to make their lives the
best first.
So, I'm not saying there's not
corruption in capitalist economies, but
it's sort of inherent in a command
economy. It's inherent because you're
giving a set of people the power to
decide who gets what, and it's
inevitably in human nature to still
decide to give themselves the most in
first.
So, that is why really why the Soviet
Union collapsed, because the command
economy simply couldn't get it done. And
let's be clear, it did not appear
inevitable. In the 1950s,
there was huge envy
in the US of what the Soviet Union was
accomplishing. They came out of a
devastating war and built a
manufacturing base that was the envy of
the entire world, even the US, almost
overnight. It was incredible.
And a lot of people questioned whether
that might after all not be the right
model. It just it turns out over about
30 years it fell apart, cuz it just
wasn't sustainable.
Now, the alternative, of course, is the
uh US economy.
The capital economy, which operates by
what the famous the father of economics,
Adam Smith, calls the invisible hand.
The notion of invisible hand is you
don't need a government to make all the
decisions, cuz the market makes it for
you. The invisible hand of the market
decides how much should get produced and
who should get it, not through any one
person making decision, but just through
people coming together in a market and
working together to make those
decisions. And that's what we'll teach
you this semester, how the market works
and how those that invisible hand can
lead through the magic of the market to
the right goods being produced and
getting in the hands of the right
people.
Okay? So, that's a huge advantage, and
it's worked. America is the richest
nation in the world, we've grown rapidly
for centuries now,
um and we are um
and and we're very successful. On the
other hand,
it leads to tremendous inequality.
Because the way the right person to have
the good is the person who can pay the
most for it.
Right? In the command economy, the right
person to have the good, corruption
aside, is who needs it the most.
If you take our kidney example, the
command economy would say, "Well, let's
find the person close to death and give
them the kidney." The capitalist economy
would say, "Let's find the person
willing to pay the most to give them the
kidney." Well, that's unfair.
And that is an inevitable outcome of a
capitalist economy. America is the most
unequal major nation in the world.
Our inequality dwarfs what we see in
other countries around the world. The
top 1% of Americans control 25% of all
the income in the US.
Which is which is at least 5% higher
than any other major nation in the
world.
Okay? So, we have large inequality
because basically
the market is inevitable in a market
that'll happen because people who want
to pay the most get the stuff.
Okay? So, that gives you the trade-off.
The consensus, I would say, among
virtually every economist
is that
a command economy is not the way to go.
The debate is within the capitalist
model
how far the government should intervene.
If you look at countries like Europe,
they have a much more interventionist
economies. You'll often hear European
countries being called socialist.
They're not socialist. Socialist means
the government controls the industry.
Socialist would be there's still
consumers who get to decide what to buy,
but the government produces everything.
The government runs the banks. The
government runs the airplanes. The
government decides how much steel to
produce. The government So, in
substance, a socialist is sort of
halfway between capitalist and command
economy.
Where the government does the
production, but market forces decide the
allocation.
That's not true in any other major
country in the world.
Okay? These countries are all different
levels of constrained capitalist
economies. They're all different widths
of those bowling alleys.
Okay?
In Europe and many European nations,
they have much more constrained
capitalist economies, much higher taxes,
much more government intervention.
Also much more equal.
And what we'll be talking about this
semester, and what I focus on much more
in my course 1441, is how do we think
about those tradeoffs?
Between a freer
economy which is larger, but leads to
more inequality than the US, and a less
free economy with less inequality.
Okay? So, to guide you to where we're
going to go, I'm really big on sort of
making sure you have a big picture of
where we are in this class. And once
again, if you're confused not just about
the little picture, but the big picture,
let's talk. I do urge people to come
talk to me. I generally, my rule is if
it's like a question about a problem
set, go see the TAs.
If it's a question about like I don't
understand a concept, or I want to just
talk about economics in general, or life
in general, or music, or whatever, then
come see me. Okay? And I really do urge
you folks to come come see me. Uh now
that I'm chairman, I have to be around
all the time. So, I'm around plenty of
time. Please just make an appointment
and come see me.
So, where we're going to go from here.
What we're going to do, like I said, is
the next few lectures we're going to map
out what makes a demand curve.
Then we're going to map out what makes a
supply curve.
Then we're going to put them together
and talk about basically, in some sense,
come back to where we started.
But now with an understanding of what
demand and supply mean, and why the
equilibrium makes sense. We'll then talk
about We'll then turn to normative
economics and talk about why the market
equilibrium is really the best outcome.
We're then going to start to talk about
where the standard We'll spend about the
first, I would say, half of the class on
the standard economic model.
The second half of the class will be
focused on where the standard model
breaks down.
What happens when there's monopolies,
like Google, effectively a monopoly on
search engines?
What happens when we want to trade with
other countries?
What happens when we have to decide how
much to save and how hard to work? What
happens when we have to decide, um where
to invest, and what to do about global
warming?
These are all the questions we'll tackle
in the second half of the class.
Okay? So, let me stop there, and I hope
I'll be seeing you all, uh every Monday
and Wednesday. Thank you.